Guide to the Duyckinck Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Duyckinck family papers
1736-1936
MS 1059
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
A Brooklyn, New York family descended from Evert Duyckinck of the Netherlands. The principal figure is Whitehead C. Duyckinck of the Yale University Class of 1865. Most of his papers consist of correspondence with former classmates on class matters. Also in the papers are legal and financial papers of the Duyckinck family (1736-1912), specifications for a house to be built on Clark Street in New York, a photograph of Evert A. Duyckinck, and assorted memorabilia.
Duyckinck family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of W. C. Duyckinck, 1933, and by purchase, 1957.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Whitehead Cornell Duyckinck was born in Brooklyn, New York, October 23, 1843. He was the son of Richard Bancker and Eliza H. (Cornell) Duyckinck.
He was the eighth generation from his paternal ancestor, Evert Duyckinck, who settled in New Amsterdam, now New York, in 1638, and in the ninth generation from his maternal ancestor, Thomas Cornell, who came from County Essex, England, and settled in Portsmouth, Rhode Island, in 1640.
After graduating from Yale College in 1865, he became a clerk with the firm of Howland & Aspinwall, at that time one of the most important and extensive shipping merchants in New York. Remaining with them three years, he then went into the free and bonded storage business, under the firm name of Mathews & Duyckinck. Retiring from this firm, he became a partner in the firm of H.A. Rogers & Co., importers, manufacturers and dealers in railway, machinist and engineers' supplies, at 50 and 52 John Street, New York, which was dissolved in 1875. He then continued in business alone until 1886, when, owing to sickness from overwork, he retired, having disposed of his business to a stock company. For a time he did not take part in any active business, but in 1891 accepted a position in the Mutual Life Insurance Company of new York, with which he was connected until his retirement, in 1914.
In his leisure time, Duyckinck wrote about his personal and family histories, publishing The Duyckinck and Allied Families in 1908, and Student Life at Yale in 1925. He was always loyal to Yale and served the class of 1865 as treasurer, secretary, custodian, and historian.
He was married on April 20, 1869, in Brooklyn, New York, to Caroline Hyde. They had three children.
Whitehead Duyckinck died of cerebral thrombosis on February 21, 1936, in Plainfield, New Jersey.
(Sources: Biographical Record of the Class of 1865, Yale College and Yale University Obituary Record, 1935-1936)
Scope and Contents
A Brooklyn, New York family descended from Evert Duyckinck of the Netherlands. The principal figure is Whitehead C. Duyckinck of the Yale University Class of 1865. Most of his papers consist of correspondence with former classmates on class matters. Also in the papers are legal and financial papers of the Duyckinck family (1736-1912), specifications for a house to be built on Clark Street in New York, a photograph of Evert A. Duyckinck, and assorted memorabilia.
Buildings -- New York (State) -- New York; Dwellings -- Estimates and costs; Families; Deeds; Duyckinck, Whitehead Cornell, 1843-1936; Duyckinck family; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1865; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory
  - Duyckinck Family
    - Miscellaneous legal and financial papers, 1736-1912 (Box 1)
      General
      See also: Inventory Box 3
    - Photograph of Evert A. Duyckinck, Circa 1860 (Box 1)
    - "Specifications of materials and labor for the masons department of a three story and basement dwelling house to be erected on the lot known as No. Clark Street...", undated (Box 1)
  - Whitehead C. Duyckinck
    - Incoming letters (mainly from Yale classmates), 1866 (Box 1)
    - Class of 1865: correspondence and memorabilia, 1865, 1890, 1915-1930, undated (Box 1)
    - Duyckinck coin collection: index, undated (Box 1)
    - Photographs of Whitehead C. Duyckinck, 1935 (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1862-1865, 1932, 1936, undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous papers, undated (Box 1)
    - Objects
      - Piece of molten glass from the ruins of the Crystal Palace, undated (Box 2)
      - Piece of the flag from Fort Ticonderoga, undated (Box 2)
      - Piece of wood from a chair on the ship Resolute of the Franklin Polar Expedition, undated (Box 2)
      - Chinese scroll, undated (Box 3)
      - Printed illustration, "Washington and Wife Visiting the Troops at Valley Forge, on Christmas Day 1777", undated (Box 3)
      - Cloth printed with drawings of Samuel Slater and historic sites in Pawtucket, Rhode Island, undated (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous legal and financial papers and class of 1865 correspondence and memorabilia, undated (Box 3)